Guide to the Sugoroku (Japanese Board Games) collection, 1896-circa 1950s RL.11796
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Sugoroku (Japanese board games) collection
1896-circa 1950
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11796
4.0 Linear Feet
Sugoroku are Japanese games similar to snakes and ladders, which in the late 19th and early 20th centuries were sometimes included in newspapers and children's magazines. Includes 26 sugoroku games (some items are double-sided), primarily dating from the 1910s to 1930s, with a few earlier and later.
Biographical / Historical
すごろく, or sugoroku, are Japanese games similar to "snakes and ladders". These types of games typically involve numbered squares, which players navigate from bottom to top using dice, and where there may be "ladders" allowing a climb ahead or "snakes" causing a fall behind. Sugoroku may vary in structure and game play, and often include instructions on how to play. In the Meiji, Taisho, and early Showa periods (1890s-1940s and later), sugoroku games were sometimes included as inserts in newspapers and children's magazines.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Sugoroku (Japanese Games) collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as purchases in 2019, from Asia Bookroom in 2021, from Daša Pahor, Ph.D., & Alexander Johnson, Ph.D. in 2021, from Rose Counsell Hozuki Books in 2022, and from Joe Fay McBride Rare Books in 2023.
Collection Overview
Includes 26 sugoroku games (some items are double-sided), primarily dating from the 1910s to 1930s, with a few earlier and later. Many games have a military theme, but others themes include animals, science, Hollywood actors, and travel.
Related Materials
興亜ナカヨシスゴロク: 幼年俱樂部新年號附錄 / Kōa nakayoshi sugoroku: Yōnen kurabu shinnengō furoku, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
日満交驩大双六. / Nichi-Man ko kan dai sugoroku, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
歐訪大飛行記念飛行遊戯. / Ōhō daihikō kinen hikō yūgi, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Sugoroku; Board games -- Japan; Sino-Japanese War, 1937-1945 -- Japan; Sino-Japanese Conflict, 1931-1933; Tanks (Military science) -- Japan; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japan; World War, 1914-1918 -- Japan; Nuclear physics
- 漫画双六 世界早のぞき (Manga sugoroku Sekai hayanzoki), 1931 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0001)
  Scope and Contents
  Publisher: Publisher not indicated (likely 新愛知 / Shin-Aichi)
  Other names associated: 堤寒三 (Tsutsumi Kanzō - art)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku with spaces for different activities and famous people all over the world, including Charlie Chaplin in Hollywood, famous sports figures, Mussolini in Italy, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 新愛知 (Shin-Aichi) (serial title) no. 4129. Appears to be this item: https://www.asiabookroom.com/pages/books/163414/kanzo-tsutsumi/manga-sugoroku-sekai-hayanozoki-a-brief-peek-at-the-world
  Dimensions: 80 x 53 cm
  Date as written: Showa 6
- 飛行機競争双六 (Hikōki kyōsō sugoroku), 1912 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0002)
  Publisher: 実業の日本社 (實業之日本社) (Jitsugyō no Nihon-sha)
  Other names associated: 明石赤子(Akashi Akako - art), 日本少年編輯局 (Nihon shōnen henshūkyoku - concept)
  Summary of Game: Take off and land your plane safely. Two routes (red and blue). Play instructions included on board
  Other Notes: Came as a bonus with 日本少年 (Nihon shōnen) (serial title) volume 7, issue 1
  Date as written: Meiji 45, January
- 勇ましい日本軍双六 (Isamashii Nihon-gun sugoroku), 1938 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0003a)
  Publisher: 大日本雄弁会 講談社 (Dai-Nihon Yūben-kai Kōdansha)
  Other names associated: 伊藤幾久造 (Itō Kikuzō), 飯塚羚児 (Iizuka Reiji - art)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku following the activities of the brave Japanese army, including grenade throwing, building railroads, night patrols, aerial dogfights, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 幼年倶楽部 (Yōnen kurabu) (serial title) - no issue listed
  Dimensions: 53 x 77 cm
  Date as written: Showa 13
- 動物モノシリ双六 (Dōbutsu monoshiri sugoroku), circa 1932 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0003b)
  Publisher: not indicated on this side
  Other names associated: 古賀忠道 (Koga Tadamichi - guidance), Tokyo Ueno Zoo director, 椛島勝一 (Kabashima Katsuichi - art)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku game with facts about zoo animals, including tigers, kangaroos, eagles, flying fish, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 幼年倶楽部 (Yōnen kurabu,) (serial title) - no issue listed
- 少年少女譚海 新年号 第ー附録：近代科学戦双六 (Shōnen shōjo tankai shinnengō Dai-ichi furoku: Kindai kagakusen sugoroku), 1935 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0004a)
  Publisher: not indicated beyond magazine title (少年少女譚海, Shōnen shōjo tankai)
  Other names associated: 村上松次郎 (Murakami Matsujirō - art)
  Summary of Game: Games are numbered (two-sided board): #1 first side of board, pictures and dice rolls listed, large circle in center "take-off"
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 少年少女譚海 (Shōnen shōjo tankai) (serial title) volume 16, issue 1
  Date as written: Showa 10
- 少年少女譚海 新年号 第３，４，５附録 (Shōnen shōjo tankai shinnengō Dai-san, yon, go furoku), 1935 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0004b)
  Publisher: Printer listed, but no publisher other than magazine title (Shōnen shōjo tankai)
  Other names associated: 村上松次郎 (Murakami Matsujirō - art), 少年少女譚海 (Shōnen shōjo tankai)
  Summary of Game: Games are numbered: #3 大空襲爆撃遊戯 (Dai kūshū bakugeki yūgi) (two-player territory control game, rules included); #4 新案マラソン競争遊戯 (Shin'an marason kyōsō yūgi) (race game around outer red track, rules included); #5 猛獣狩点取遊戯 (Mōjū-gari tentori yūgi) (4-player point-taking big game hunting game. Requires 12 cut-out animal cards, not present; rules included on board)
- 戦車双六 (Sensha sugoroku), circa 1932 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0005a)
  Publisher: not indicated
  Other names associated: 陸軍機甲本部 (Rikugun kikō honbu, the Army armored vehicle/tank headquarters - guidance)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku with photographic images of tanks and facts about them. (Vendor note: photos are from the Battle of Nomonhan/Khalkhin Gol, in which Japanese forces fought mechanized units from the Soviet Union)
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 機械化 (Kikaika) #13 - Duke holds original Kikaika issues
  Dimensions: 20" x 27.5"
- 現代戦車の現れるまで (Gendai no sensha no arawareru made), circa 1932 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0005b)
  Other names associated: none indicated
  Summary of Game: Diagram of modern tank, images of tanks and armored war vehicles through history. Short text with same title, describing the evolution of the tank
  Other Notes: Bonus with 機械化 (Kikaika) #13 - Duke holds original Kikaika issues
- 欧州大戦遊戯 (Ōshū taisen yūgi), 1916 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0006)
  Publisher: 大日本雄弁会 (Dai-Nihon Yūben-kai)
  Other names associated: 小林永二郎 (Kobayashi Eijiro - art), 尺秀三郎 (Seki Hidesaburō - concept)
  Summary of Game: Allied forces vs. German (whole board)
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 少年倶楽部 (Shōnen kurabu) (serial title) volume 3, issue 1
  Date as written: Taisho 5, January
- 青島占領双六 (Seitō senryō sugoroku), 1915 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0007)
  Other names associated: 有本芳水 (Arimoto Hōsui - guidance), poet; 川端龍子 (Kawabata Ryūshi - art), Nihonga painter
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku game about the siege/battle of Seitō (Qingdao/Tsingtao, China). Players play as either the army or navy attacking the German army at Qingdao, encountering various challenges, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as new year's bonus with 日本少年 (Nihon shōnen) in Taisho 4 (1915)
  Dimensions: 21" x 31"
- 軍国飛行双六 (Gunkoku hikō sugoroku), 1916 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0008)
  Publisher: 飛行少年研究会 (Hikō shōnen kenkyūkai)
  Other names associated: 谷洗馬 (Tani Senba - art), famous 20th century illustrator; 仲摩鐵堂 (Nakama Tetsudō - guidance). Some images specifically signed in romanized letters "G. Senba Tani" and dated 1915 or 1916
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku game featuring major activities/skills of airforce/army aviators. Images include dogfights, sea battles, reconaissance, zepplins, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 飛行少年 (Hikō shōnen), volume 2, issue 1, January 1st Taisho 5
  Dimensions: 21.25" x 30.75"
  Date as written: 1916 (Taisho 5)
- 原子双六 (Genshi sugoroku (envelope)), circa 1949-1950 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0009a)
  Publisher: 日本発明新聞社 (Nihon Hatsumei Shinbunsha)
  Other names associated: 日本発明新聞社 (Nihon Hatsumei Shinbunsha) (Japan Invention Newspaper) editors - guidance, 下馬三郎 (Shimouma Saburō - art)
  Summary of Game: In commemoration of the Nobel prize awarded to Dr. Yukawa (1949)
  Other Notes: Original envelope
- 原子双六 (Genshi sugoroku (board)), circa 1949-1950 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0009b)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku game with facts about nuclear/atomic science (incl. images of cyclotron, Marie Curie, Alfred Nobel, Yukawa Hideki, Bohr model of the atom, x-rays, etc.)
  Other Notes: Game board
  Dimensions: 75 x 52 cm for game board
- 陸海大激戦双六 (Riku-kai dai-gekisen sugoroku), 1917 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0010a)
  Publisher: 博文館 (Hakubunkan)
  Other names associated: 金子士郎 (Kaneko Shiro - art), 少年世界編輯局 (Shōnen sekai henshūkyoku - concept)
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku board game, attached description says "Siberian expedition and occupation" - large color images, numbered
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 少年世界 (Shōnen sekai) (serial title) volume 33, issue 1
  Date as written: Taisho 6, January
- 甘賀珍助竹刀修業 (Amaga Chinsuke shinai shūgyō), 1917 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0010b)
  Other names associated: no other attributions
  Summary of Game: Sugoroku board game about Amaga Chinsuke & shinai (bamboo sword) training - unrelated to reverse-side game. (Only printed in green)
- 皇軍萬歳双六 (Kōgun banzai sugoroku), 1940 (Box 1, Item RL11796-A-0018)
  Publisher: Ōhashi Kо̄kichi 大橋光吉
  Other names associated: Editor and Writer (編輯兼發行人): Utagawa Hitoshi 宇田川釣, Nakamura Hoshika 中村星果, concept (案), Sawai Ichisaburо̄ 澤井一三郎, illustrations (畫)
  Other notes: Magazine: Shōjo kurabu 少女倶楽部 ("Young Girls' Club"), 第十八巻: Issue no. 18, 第一號附録: Supplement no. 1
  Dimensions: 53x79 cm
  Date as written: Showa 15.
  Map of China and Manchuria printed on reverse.
- 世界列強競争遊戯 (Sekai rekkyō kyōsō yūgi), 1917 (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0011)
  Publisher: 大日本雄弁会 (printed by 博文館) (Dai-Nihon Yūben-kai (printed by Hakubunkan))
  Other names associated: 佐藤信夫 (Satō Nobuo [?] - concept/design)
  Summary of Game: "World powers race", 8 countries, playing pieces for military branches/groups, rules of play on board
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 少年世界 (Shōnen sekai) (serial title) volume 4, issue 1
- 最新兵器双六 (Saishin heiki sugoroku), circa 1910s-1940s (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0012)
  Publisher: 日光社 (Nikkō-sha)
  Summary of Game: "Cutting-edge weapon sugoroku", each place on the board features a cutting-edge military weapon
  Other Notes: No notes or information about rules or origin present
  Dimensions: 54 x 39 cm
- 貯金双六 (Chokin sugoroku), circa 1942 (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0013)
  Summary of Game: Small sugoroku board about saving money as patriotic duty, route to happiness, and protection in emergencies
  Other Notes: Came as bonus with 安田貯蓄貯金読本 (Yasuda chochiku chokin dokuhon) - 安田貯蓄貯金 (Yasuda Chochiku Ginkō appears to be name of bank)
  Dimensions: 11"x15"
- 飛行機双六 (Hikōki sugoroku), circa 1930s (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0014)
  Publisher: スモーヤ 稲葉春吉 (Sumōya Inaba Haruyoshi)
  Other names associated: 稲葉春吉 (Inaba Haruyoshi) appears to be the personal name associated with corporate name スモーヤ Sumo-ya / Sumōya
  Summary of Game: Airplane sugoroku, with spaces for refuling, parachuting, night flying, etc.
  Dimensions: 54 x 38 cm
- 支那事變皇軍大勝 (Shina Jihen kogun taisho sugoroku (front)), 1939 (Oversize-folder 1, Item RL11796-A-0015a)
  Publisher: 主婦の友 (Shufu no tomo)
  Other names associated: 主婦の友編輯局 (Shufu no tomo henshūkyoku - guidance), 嶺田弘 (Mineda Hiroshi - art), illustrator
  Summary of Game: Next to title: 皇軍勇士慰問・銃後家庭慰問 (Kōgun yūshi imon / Jūgo katei imon) "Condolences/sympathy for the brave soldiers of the imperial army, condolences/sympathy for those on the homefront". Sugoroku game about the Sino-Japanese war, interim government of Manchuria, activities supporting the troops at war, etc. Includes un-cut die template and cards with silhouettes of planes, ships, etc.
  Other Notes: Came as a new year's bonus with 主婦の友 for Showa 14, v.23 issue 1.
  Dimensions: 25" x 37"
- お正月の新しい家庭娯楽大特輯 (Oshōgatsu no atarashii katei goraku daitokushū (reverse)), 1939 (Oversize-folder 1, Item RL11796-A-0015b)
  Other names associated: 永鳥眞雄 (Nagatori Sanao) listed under the coin fortune-telling section
  Summary of Game: Variety of games to play at home, includes small board game in center, games to play as a family at home (including "indoor boat race", "bean-throwing battle", "find the spy", etc - many are war/battle-themed), a fortune-telling chart using coins, and fortune-telling based on zodiac animals
  Other Notes: Came as a new year's bonus with 主婦の友 (Shufu no tomo) Showa 14, v.23 issue 1.
- 日本周遊雙六 (Nihon shūyū sugoroku), 1896 December (Oversize-folder 1, Item RL11796-A-0016)
  Other names associated: 水野年方 (Mizuno Toshikata - art), ukiyoe-e and Nihonga artist
  Summary of Game: Travel-themed sugoroku with landmarks/famous locations around Japan, including Ise Grand Shrine, Tokyo, Niigata, Nikko, Izumo Grand Shrine, and notably Ryūkyū, Taiwan ("Japan's new territory/holding after the great success of the Sino-Japanese War" with an image of locals waving Japanese flags & imperial soldiers), Chishima (the contested Kuril islands), and Bakan (the Treaty of Shimonoseki)
  Dimensions: 24.5" x 35"
- 征空すごろく、世界航空路圖 (Seizora sugoroku, Sekai kōkū michizu), circa 1930 (Oversize-folder 1, Item RL11796-A-0017, Item RL11796-A-0019)
  Publisher: 大阪毎日新聞 (Ōsaka Mainichi Shinbun)
  Other names associated: No attributions given
  Summary of Game: 新時代教育遊戯 (Shin-jidai kyōiku yūgi - a new-era educational game) (subtitle on upper-right of board). This large format color Japanese world map doubles as a 'Sugoroku' gameboard and was issued by the Osaka Mainichi Shinbun newspaper as a 1930 'New Year's Supplement', a special reward to its readers. The stylized map game has players explore every part of the globe by either airplane or Zeppelin airship. adorned with their flags. All major cities are labelled and connected by flight routes, while images of famous aircraft, such as Charles Lindbergh's 'Spirit of St. Louis' (the first plane to cross the Atlantic in 1927) and the German Zeppelin airships, shown crossing the seas. The margins feature photographic images associated with different parts of the world, including buildings, archeological sites, animals, or people in local clothing. In the lower right corner, the map features the directions for playing. 'The Easiest Way', as Interpreted by The David Rumsey Map Collection: "Departing from Osaka [1] and moving to all the places in order of 2, 3, 4, you then return to Tokyo [52]. the player who reaches there first is the winner. "throw the dice and proceed as many places as the number you cast..." In the upper right, text informs players of distances between locations, with basic geographic facts. The legend, toward the bottom of the map oval, shows 5 types of red lines & 1 square: 1. well-known large aircraft route (refers to Zeppelin, seen center of map) 2. first-class limited time route 3. liner air route 4. air route already mastered/controlled/conquered 5. planned route. main localities [red square inside black square]." References: David Rusmey Map Collection: 7926.000.
  Other Notes: Came as new year's bonus with 大阪毎日新聞 (Osaka Mainichi newspaper), v.1 no. 6755
  Dimensions: 107 x 77 cm
  Sources: dealer description provided by Daša Pahor, Ph.D., & Alexander Johnson, Ph.D.
- 紙名尽寿語六 (Shimei zukushi sugoroku), 1928 (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0020)
  Publisher: 伊勢辰 (Isetatsu)
  Other namesassociated: none given.
  Summary of game: This sugoroku depicts various forms of Japanese paper and papermaking techniques. The red column gives several types of paper, including tanzaku, chiyogami, hōshogami, minogami, ganpishi, torinokogami, fusumagami, and Asakusagami. The starting square depicts two female papermakers at work. The winning square depicts the Seven Gods of Fortune. This sugoroku is considerably smaller by genre standards.
  Other Notes: This game board uses an alternative rendering of the term sugoroku. It is rendered as 寿語六, while more typically the term appears as 双六.
  Dimensions: 38 x 25 cm.
- 活劇王双六 (Katsugeki Ō Sugoroku), circa 1950s (Box 2, Item RL11796-A-0021)
  Publisher: ナゴヤ玩具 (Nagoya Omocha)
  No other names present on item.
  39cm x 54cm